Register of the Vladimir Iakovlevich Tolmachev Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vladimir Iakovlevich Tolmachev papers
1909-1947
2001C45
Hoover Institution Archives
2 microfilm reels (0.3 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the archeology of China and to Russian émigré affairs.
Tolmachev, Vladimir Iakovlevich, d. 1947
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
V. Ia. Tolmachev was born in Shadrinskii uezd, Permskaia guberniia, on 21 November 1876 (O.S.). Upon graduation from the Ekaterinburg gimnaziia, he entered St. Petersburg University, where he studied in the physics and mathematics department, and simultaneously audited courses at the Academy of Arts. But his primary interest was archeology, and in 1900 he transferred to the Archeological Institute. Every summer was spent on expedition, and upon graduation from the Institute he went to work digging up artifacts in the Ural-Volga region. Many of the results of his scientific work appeared in Drevnosti Urala, which commenced publication in 1913.
The Civil War brought him to Chita, where he remained until 1922, continuing archeological research and teaching. His career in Harbin was associated with archeological and paleontological finds of great significance all across Manchuria. He was a curator of the Museum of the Society for the Study of Manchuria (Obshchestvo issledovaniia Man'chzhurskogo kraia). He also wrote many articles on the commodities markets for Manchurian goods, such as soy beans. Most of the writings in his collection deal with Manchurian and Chinese archeology, culture, and agriculture. He left Harbin for Shanghai in the mid-1930s. Tolmachev apparently died in 1947.
Chronology
? Born, Russia
1918 Lecturer, Narodnyi Universitet, Moscow, Russia
1928 Author, Zernovye produkty kul'turnykh polevykh rastenii Severnoi Man'chzhurii
1947 Died, China
Scope and Content Note
V. Ia. Tolmachev was a professor of archaeology and zoology in interwar China (Manchuria). He founded and organized the commercial/industrial and archeological sections of the Harbin state museum and the Railway Museum there, of which he was curator for 10 years. The collection contains his speeches and writings on a variety of themes associated with archeology, ancient history, biology, zoology and related studies. Many of the underlined titles listed in SPEECHES AND WRITINGS are in fact limited edition off-prints of his articles in "Vestnik Man'chzhurii." There is also a small amount of correspondence and notes on Russian philately (SUBJECT FILE/Stamp collecting).
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Archaeology--China.; China.; Russia.; Russians--China.
- Biographical File, 1937-1947 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Calling cards, correspondence regarding the distribution of Tolmachev's estate, curriculum vitae, and subject file relating to an exhibition of Tolmachev's artworks, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1921-1941 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, and., 1925-1938 undated (Box 1-2)
  Lectures, articles, books, notes, maps and sketches, arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1909-1940 (Box 2)
  Clippings, correspondence, notes and lectures, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 2)
  Album of prints depicting items unearthed on archeological expeditions in China
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1937-1947 (Box 1)
  - Calling cards (both Tolmachev's and others') (Folder 1: 1)
  - Correspondence of the executors of Tolmachev's estate with various museums and cultural institutions regarding the distribution of his scientific and published works, 1947 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Curriculum vitae (Folder 1: 3)
  - Subject file - Art exhibition. (Folder 1: 4)
    Includes catalog of Tolmachev's works exhibited and comments of critics
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1921-1941
  - General, and, 1936-1941 undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Unidentified, and, 1921-1935 undated (Folder 1: 6)
  - Egorov, Konstantin Fedorovich, 1938 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Nedel'skii, Aleksandr T.
    General note
    See SUBJECT FILE/Stamp collecting
  - Princis, K., 1935 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Satovskii-Rzhevskii, G. G.
    See Ural'skii oblastnoi muzei estestvoznaniia
  - Tallgren, A. M., 1937 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Tolmachev, N., 1937-1940 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Ural'skii oblastnoi muzei estestvoznaniia, n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
    Written on same paper as draft letter to G. G. Satovskii-Rzhevskii, n.d.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, and, 1925-1938 undated
  - General, n.d.
    - Chapter of an untitled book on archeological digs in Eastern Mongolia, n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
      Holograph
    - Notes, citations from books, maps, and sketches of archeological finds (Folder 1: 13-15)
      Holograph and typescript
  - "Kitaiskaia farmakopeia,", n.d. (Box-folder 2: 1)
    Typescript
  - "Kitaiskaia meditsina,", n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Kitaiskaia muzyka,", n.d. (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Kitaiskii teatr,", n.d. (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Rodinovedenie v Finliandii," (Folder 2: 5)
    Holograph. Includes background materials
  - "Skify i kitaitsy," lecture, n.d. (Folder 2: 6)
  - Untitled book or part of book on Manchurian pre-history, n.d. (Folder 2: 7)
  - "Vremia,", n.d. (Folder 2: 8)
  - Drevnosti Man'chzhurii: Razvaliny Bei-Chena, 1925 (Folder 2: 9)
    Printed copy
  - Bai-Chen, 1927 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Prigotovlenie krakhmal'noi vizigi v Severnoi Man'chzhurii, 1927 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Ostatki neoliticheskoi kul'tury bliz Khailara, 1928 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Zernovye produkty kul'turnykh polevykh rastenii Severnoi Man'chzhurii, 1928 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Kitaiskie tsynovki: Ikh rasprostranenie i khoziaistvennoe primenenie v Severnoi Man'chzhurii, 1930 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Kitaiskie pishchevye produkty iz maslianistykh i krakhmalistykh bobov, 1931 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Priadil'nye rasteniia i kitaiskie tkani iz nikh na rynke Severnoi Man'chzhurii, 1931 (Folder 2: 16)
  - K voprosu o paleolite v Severnoi Man'chzhurii, 1933 (Folder 2: 17)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - Zemledel'cheskie orudiia man'chzhurskogo krest'ianstva, 1934 (Folder 2: 18)
  - "Les antiquités scythes en Chine," Eurasia Septentrionalis Antiqua, 1935 (Folder 2: 19)
  - "Evgenika," public lecture given in Shanghai, China, 1938 March 22 (Folder 2: 20)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes clippings advertising and reviewing lecture
- SUBJECT FILE, 1909-1940
  - Stamp collecting. (Folder 2: 21)
    Includes clippings, correspondence with Aleksandr T. Nedel'skii (Alexander T. Nedelsky), 1937-1939, regarding stamp collecting, a list of fellow collectors, and notes on rare Russian issues
  - Miscellany. (Folder 2: 22)
    Clippings on various subjects and a compilation of lectures by N. V. Kiuner entitled Istoricheskii ocherk razvitiia osnov kitaiskoi material'noi i dukhovnoi kul'tury, published in mimeograph form in Vladivostok in 1909
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d. (Folder 2: 23)